Okay בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody.
Today's דף daf is ע׳. Ayin. We start the next פרק perek
המדיר. Hamadir. I should just mention briefly that there's a little debate
in the ראשונים Rishonim about the order of the פרקים. prokim. But
anyway, this one,
so but this is the order that we've got, so this is
the order we're going with.
Part of the problem is that the משנה Mishnah keeps on weaving
the פרקים prokim in and out of different considerations about the בעל's
ba'al חיוב מזונות. chiyuv mezonot. The two big themes are of course
the חיוב מזונות, chiyuv mezonot, מעשה ידיים ma'aseh yadayim sort of pair,
and the issue about sex and that comes up in terms of
people that are not performing, and מורדת moredet and נדר neder etc.
and it comes up in terms of quantity and what is the
standard obligations. And the פרקים prokim keep on sort of weaving in
and out between those two themes which leads to some question of
exactly what the right order is. Anyway, so the last משנה Mishnah
of the last פרק perek dealt
with giving over to the hands of a שליש, shalish, a third
party, one's responsibility in terms of taking care of one's daughters. So
it started first of all with the case of the father dying
and what is the issue about the assumed to be the junior,
the dowry that he's going to give her, and then into the
issue about also about
having some other party create basically setting up a trust. Okay, some
of that wasn't to strict obligations to his daughters, but dealing with
those types of scenarios, not just wife but of daughters. Now we
go back to the issue about wife and about the obligation of
מזונות. mezonot. So let's take a look and there's also going to
be a role of a שליש shalish here, a third party, which
might be what the transition is. המדיר אשתו מליהנות לו. Hamadir ishto
mileihanos lo. Okay,
if somebody takes a vow that his wife cannot derive any benefit
from him. מאי הנאתי Mai hana'ati is אסורה asura to my wife.
You can make a vow that your stuff is forbidden to somebody
else. So your stuff is not just physical objects, but any הנאה
hana'ah deriving from you. We'll talk about that is forbidden on your
wife. And the גמרא's Gemara going to focus specifically about his obligation
of מזונות. mezonot. So Michael says well what about the מצוות עונה
mitzvas Onah and how can that how can he take a vow
against the מצווה mitzvah of עונה. Onah. So I'll get back to
that in a minute, but the גמרא Gemara sort of ignores עונה.
Onah. עד שלושים יום יעמיד פרנס. Ad shloshim yom ya'amid parnas.
Up to 30 days he can have a third party set up
to provide for his wife's מזונות. mezonot. Now the גמרא's Gemara of
course going to ask, but if he's arranging for a third party
to take care of it, then she's getting benefit from him. This
third party is like his שליח shaliach ultimately it's coming as benefit
that's coming through him. So why isn't that just as problematic? So
we'll see that in the גמרא. Gemara. But up to 30 days
we can manage through a third party. יותר מכאן יוציא ויתן כתובה.
Yeter mikan yotzi v'yiten kesuvah. More than 30 days
he has to divorce her and give a כתובה. kesuvah. We cannot
maintain this relationship, even though we had learned in an earlier פרק
perek that they could live separate and he could be providing for
her if she's living not only if he's away, but if they've
taken up separate domicile. It says they're supposed to eat together and
have sex together every Friday night, but even though that's acceptable for
them to live separate, here, even if they're living together, to be
in this type of a relationship, maybe specifically one where there's a
נדר, neder, so it's clearly there's some contention between them.
In this relationship more than 30 days is not seen as sustainable.
Okay, we will see also in the גמרא Gemara whether does that
mean that his נדר neder is סתם stam and we still give
him 30 days to try to figure it out, to try to
maybe get a היתר heter for his נדר, neder, or if it's
a נדר neder for less than 30 days or more than 30
days. What's the 30 days? Is the נדר neder indefinite but we
wait 30 days to see if he can work it out and
once he hasn't worked it out in 30 days then they gotta
separate, or if it's a נדר neder for under 30 days we
allow it, more than 30 days, or up to 30 days we
allow it, more than 30 days we say they have to get
divorced.
Okay, so is it generally סתם נדר stam neder is for 30
days?
No, סתם נזירות stam nezirut is for 30 days, but if a
person just says a סתם נדר stam neder then it's indefinite, yeah.
Okay one minute. Okay רבי יהודה אומר. Rabbi Yehuda Omer. So רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says בישראל חודש אחד. B'Yisrael chodesh echad.
For a ישראל, Yisrael, meaning a non-כהן, kohen, we give them one
month. יקיים, Yekayem,
if it's up to one month then we allow it to maintain,
we allow them to stay married. ושניים, U'shnayim, if it's more than
one month, presumably into the second month, יוציא ויתן כתובה. yotzi v'yiten
kesuvah. Then he has to actually divorce and give the כתובה. kesuvah.
That's what we said before. But the חידוש chiddush now is the
difference between him and a כהן. kohen. ולכהן, U'l'kohen, if it's however
it's a wife of a כהן, kohen, to a wife of a
כהן kohen there's no turning back after divorce. You can't say oh
let's get remarried. So in the case of a כהן kohen we
want to give it a little bit more time. שניים יקיים, Shnayim
yekayem, or
we want to have a little bit more tolerance. So up to
two months we allow it, up to and including. ושלושה, U'shlosha, into
the third month, only then יוציא ויתן כתובה. yotzi v'yiten kesuvah. But
we say that you have to go ahead and get divorced and
give a כתובה. kesuba. המדיר אשתו, Hamadir ishto,
let's get through the משנה mishna then I'll go back to questions
and also other points that I referred to. המדיר אשתו שלא תטעום
אחד מכל הפירות יוציא ויתן כתובה. Hamadir ishto shelo sitam echad mikol
hapirot yotzi veyitein kesuba. If someone takes a vow that his wife
can't get any taste, any fruit—and fruit is a very catch-all category,
right, includes also grains and whatever—anyway, then he has to divorce her
and give the כתובה. kesuba. Now the question here is, first of
all, how can he do that? He can't make a vow... he
can make a vow that his wife can't eat his fruit, but
how can he say any fruit? So the גמרא Gemara basically says
that the wife took the vow and he was מקיים mikayem it.
He could have been מיפר meifer it but he was מקיים mikayem
it. So even so one wonders why is that related to getting
divorced? How does getting divorced change whether she's eating the fruit or
not eating the fruit? So this is like this is much more,
you know, unclear what's exactly going on here and we'll have to
work, we'll have to get to that in the גמרא. Gemara. רבי
יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, but now we see a similar point
that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda wants to put the brakes on this
but by a case of a כהן. kohein. רבי יהודה אומר בישראל
יום אחד יקיים שנים יוציא ויתן כתובה. Rabbi Yehuda omer beyisrael yom
echad yekayeim shnayim yotzi veyitein kesuba. By ישראל Yisrael we give,
if this vow just for one day we can't tolerate this because
to say no fruit is allowed, you know, we won't even tolerate
it for more than one day. But so up to two days
and if it goes into the second day, get a divorce, get
a כתובה. kesuba. ובכהן, Uvikohein, but by כהן kohein we're going to
tolerate it more. שנים יקיים Shnayim yekayeim we give two days, שלושה
יוציא ויתן כתובה. shlosha yotzi veyitein kesuba. Okay, three you give a
כתובה, kesuba, divorce. המדיר אשתו שלא תתקשט באחד מכל המינים, Hamadir ishto
shelo siskasheit be'echad mikol haminim, a man takes a vow that his
wife cannot, you know, adorn herself with anything, either any jewelry or
also מינים minim here רש"י Rashi says תתקשט tiskasheit also includes like
perfume and therefore, you know, you can't use even one perfume, okay,
take a vow that all Chanel No. 5 is אסור. assur. All
right, so again how does the husband take the vow against the
wife about that?
She says that Chanel is not to be allowed.
Was she really? Oh wow, okay, so anyway so it says that
actually that she took the vow and the husband was מקיים mikayem
it. We're going to say again in the
גמרא. Gemara. Just one perfume, not all. אחד, Echad, right, אחד. echad.
Actually I should have said that before, I'm sorry, I didn't say
it before. It was the same before שלא תטעום אחד מכל הפירות.
shelo sitam echad mikol hapirot. It was just one fruit that she
says, kumquats or whatever, I'm sorry, I should have made that clear.
Right.
He says she doesn't use it, right?
This is still... yeah. So that's, so the חידוש chiddush of the
משנה mishna is is that this is such a big deal even
though it's just one thing that's being forbidden. Of course again the
question is what's the husband's role in making this vow a vow?
She really took the vow. But yes, I ran through that before
but yes, it was אחד מכל הפירות. echad mikol hapirot. I misread
it, it was not all, it's one fruit, just kumquats are forbidden,
just for this perfume is forbidden, nevertheless that's intolerable. So יוציא ויתן
כתובה. yotzi veyitein kesuba. So you get, you do get divorced and
you give a כתובה. kesuba. Now we have another interesting position not
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who would presumably make some distinction between a
ישראל Yisrael and a כהן, kohein, but רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. רבי
יוסי אומר בעניות שלא נתן קצבה, Rabbi Yosi omer be'aniyos shelo nasan
kitzva, by poor women who normally don't put on, you know, jewelry
or perfume, then it's only get a divorce if it's an indefinite
vow, if there's some end period it's then it's okay, how long
an end period? 20 years? So we'll see what the קצבה kitzva
is in the גמרא, Gemara, but it has to be indefinite or
a long time. ובעשירות, Uva'ashiros, but rich women, this is a real,
you know, difficult because they generally do put on perfume and jewelry
and so on, שלושים יום, shloshim yom, we tolerate it for 30
days, more than 30 days we do not. So in the last
two you have this case about something that's really not him vowing,
it's her vowing. It's a certain amount of self-denial.
What's not and the חידוש chiddush partly the חידוש chiddush is only
one fruit, only one piece of jewelry, but the other thing that's
difficult about this is what does that have to do with their
marriage? Why is he the one divorcing her? How's that related to
their marriage? But the first part, which is what we're going to
focus on today, is much easier, it is about their marriage, it's
about him taking the vow and him getting out of his חיוב
מזונות. chiyuv mezonos. Now I want to say two things and then
I see that Michael has a question. One thing is why is
he focusing on מזונות mezonos and not on עונה? onah? So if
you take a look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says המדיר אשתו,
hamadir ishto, the first רש"י, Rashi, אינה תשמיש נאסר עליה דמשועבד לה.
einas nash tashmisho ne'esar aleiha de'meshubad lah.
He can't, maybe the vow, the word מליהנות mileihanot
includes all הנאה, hana'a, includes עונה, onah, but it doesn't take effect
on the עונה onah because he already has an obligation in עונה
onah and therefore that's hers, he doesn't have a right, you know,
that vow isn't חל chal on it, she has a שיעבוד shibud
on it, essentially her property as it were. הלכך בשביל התשמיש אין
לנו לכוף להוציא וליתן כתובה. Hilkach bishvil hatashmish ein lanu lakof lehotzi
ulyitein kesuba. Okay? ואנא מזונות בגמרא פריך ומשועבד לה. Ve'annas mezonos begemara
parich ve'ameshubad lah. So the
גמרא's Gemara going to deal with the מזונות mezonos aspect as well,
but רש"י Rashi says it's obvious עונה's onah off the table because
עונה onah he's got a חיוב chiyuv for. Now of course the
problem here is is that what is the difference between why is
it more obvious by עונה onah than it is by מזונות? mezonos?
So what רש"י Rashi somewhat suggests, although he doesn't say it explicitly,
but he somewhat suggests is is that maybe there's a difference between
like one is דאורייתא... de'oraissa... Right like תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos* says like
תוספות Tosfos, *Tosafos* says that it sounds like what רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
is getting at although רש"י Rashi *Rashi* isn't explicit is that עונה
*Ona* is a biblical obligation and therefore it's clear that the vow
can't take effect whereas
whereas you know מזונות mezonos. *Mezonos* is only Rabbinic and therefore that
it's clear that I'm sorry no I misstated that that's תוספות'ס Tosafos's
*Tosafos's* point oh I'm sorry let's take a look at תוספות Tosfos
*Tosafos* okay המדיר אשתו מתשמיש *Hamadir ishto mitashmish* let's take a look
תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos* says the following פירוש בקונטרס *Peirush Bakonteres* דאין עונת
תשמישה *de-ein onash tashmisha* first תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos* דאין עונת תשמישה נאסר
עליו דמשתעבד לה *de-ein onash tashmisha ne'esar alav d'amishtabed lah* משמע מתוך
פירושה שיש בלשון זה איסור עונת תשמיש Tashmish *mashma mitoch peirushah sheyesh
balashon
zeh issur onash tashmish* one minute
no I'm sorry
I'm thinking about a different רש"י Rashi *Rashi* just one second
there's some discussion here about what's דאורייתא de'oraisa. *De'oraisa* what's
דרבנן derabbanan, *De'rabanan*
one minute hold on
okay I'm not finding it I'm sorry there's some issue here about
whether
the מזונות mezonos *Mezonos* is different that it's דרבנן derabbanan *De'rabanan* or
whether you know or whether מזונות mezonos? *Mezonos* is דאורייתא de'oraisa. *De'oraisa*
but I am not finding it right now so we'll just bracket
that for now okay so anyway so there's one issue why the
why it does not here take effect on עונה *Ona* so רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* says that's because you're already משועבד *meshubad* to עונה *Ona*
and that's why it's not but of course you're משועבד *meshubad* to
מזונות mezonos? *Mezonos* as well so the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* is going
to ask the מזונות mezonos *Mezonos* question whereas תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos* says
that the basic difference is that somehow just the language ליהנות *lehanos*
in the generic is understood to mean מזונות mezonos *Mezonos* and not
עונה *Ona* so it's not that somehow that there's some fundamental reason
that עונה *Ona* is more excluded like you're more obligated by עונה
*Ona* than you are by מזונות Mezonot, *Mezonos* but just somehow the
generic language is somehow interpreted to mean מזונות Mezonot. *Mezonos* and not
עונה *Ona* that's what the sense that we give it the other
point that I wanted to make I have to go back to
that other thing that I was thinking about but the other point
I wanted to make is what does יוציא yotzi ויתן כתובה *yotzi
veyitein kesuvah* mean this is a very important this is about like
as we're seeing a lot of the issues that we've come across
in כתובות *Kesuvos* interestingly you know you'd expect some of these to
be in גיטין *Gittin* but they're really in כתובות *Kesuvos* because of
questions about when a husband is forced to give a גט get
*Get* to his wife the reason it's more in כתובות *Kesuvos* than
it is in גיטין *Gittin* is because גיטין *Gittin* has more to
do with the actual execution and delivery of the גט get, *Get*
whereas כתובות *Kesuvos* has to do with the nature of the marriage
are people doing what they're supposed to be doing in marriage when
is the marriage considered viable and not viable and under what circumstances
do we say that the woman is loses her כתובה *Kesuvah* because
she's not doing her obligation or the husband you know have to
divorce her and give her כתובה *Kesuvah* and the husband is the
one to blame and so on so a lot of interesting issues
about when do we force a divorce come up in כתובות *Kesuvos*
so if you remember we already saw the discussion about if the
woman basically is refusing to have sex with her husband so she
she loses her כתובה *Kesuvah* but the real important debate of the
ראשונים *Rishonim* is fine she loses her כתובה *Kesuvah* but do we
force the husband to give her a divorce do we basically say
you know that we're not going to force her to live with
a guy she says she can't have sex with so there's the
position of the רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* that we do force the husband
to give a divorce which basically means that if the woman's willing
to forego the כתובה *Kesuvah* she can always initiate divorce proceedings by
just saying that I can't live with my husband I find him
repulsive I can't have sex with him so that was a very
very big issue there here the husband is clearly to blame and
the language of the משנה Mishna *Mishnah* is יוציא yotzi ויתן כתובה
*yotzi veyitein kesuvah* so how much does that really mean that we
would physically go to the point of using physical force it's actually
I just heard on NPR I was driving back from Pittsburgh the
other day so you know I listen to a lot of whatever
Talk Radio so anyway the famous they have a segment on This
American Life a segment called Stuck in the Middle where there people
sort of in these situations they can't get out of anyway one
of them was about עגונה *Agunah* and they actually interviewed רבקה *Rivkah*
עליה השלום *alav hashalom* Rivkah Haut and it was about the guys
that basically who was that guy that's now being held on conspiracy
charges felony charges for the rabbi for hiring these guys to kidnap
and beat up men so okay so we know they actually used
to beat up people at least through the courts so how much
does יוציא yotzi *yotzi* mean that we force him actually with physical
force to divorce so if you take a look at תוספות Tosfos
*Tosafos* יוציא ויתן כתובה *yotzi
veyitein kesuvah* תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos* says נראה לרי
דבכל הנהך דקתני
במתניתין יוציא *nireh le-Ri de-bechol hanach de-katani bematnisin yotzi* תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos*
says היינו שכופין אותו *haynu she-kofin oso* we force him דכיון דלא
כדין עביד *de-keivan she-lo kedin avid*
since he's acting improperly כופין להוציא kofin lehotzi, *kofin lehotzi* כדאשכחן בחולץ
*k'ashkachan becholitz* etc. etc. and then he says like this the last
narrow line of תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos* דכפייה דהתם במילי *de-kfiyah de-hasam bemilei*
you can't say that this other כפייה *kfiyah* that's referred to
in
Sticks and stones will break my bones, right? So do we use
words or do we use sticks? Okay. My mother always told me
to use my words. אחדא, number one, דבדברים לא יוסר עבד, debidvarim
lo yivaser eved, is that with words with words you're not going
to remonstrate a slave, meaning words only go so far. Sometimes you
gotta use sticks to get, you know, this guy's acting obstinate, sometimes
you gotta actually use sticks. Okay. And then he goes on etcetera
to prove it. Okay. So he so he has a whole long
discussion when do we actually use physical force and when do we
just try to use persuasion, but he basically is of the strong
opinion that we use physical force. And then תוספות Tosfos says like
this,
ופסק ר"ח, uphasak Rach, you see where it says פסק ר"ח, pasak
Rach, רבנו חננאל, Rabbeinu Chananel, it's about ten lines down in the
wide lines near the end of the line. Okay.
משום ש"מ mishum shin mem was? I forgot, I didn't look that
up.
משום שמע מינה. mishum shama mina. What does that mean?
Oh, משם. misham. Oh, משם שמע מינה, misham shama mina, oh, not
משם. mishem. I was thought it was משם. mishem. Okay. Okay, ופסק
ר"ח משם שמע מינה, uphasak Rach misham shama mina, from there we
can see, right, I thought it was a name of a ספר,
sefer, שאין כופין אלא היכא דמפורש בהדיא כופין. she'ein kofin ela heicha
demeforesh behedya kofin. Okay. We do not use physical force unless it's
explicit in the גמרא. Gemara אבל היכא דאמרו רבנן יוציא, aval heicha
de'amru rabanan yotzi, when it just says he should divorce her, but
it doesn't say כופין להוציא, kofin lehotzi, אומרין לו, omrin lo, we
say, כחיובא דחכמים להוציא, kechiyuva dechachamim lehotzi, the Rabbis obligated you. We
just use our words and persuasion. ואם לא תוציא מותרין לקרותך עבריינא.
ve'im lo totzi mutarin likrocha avaryana. And if he doesn't, then we
call him a sinner, you know, there's other forms of sort of
social, you know,
sort of pressure. אבל לכפותו, aval lechfoso, to physically force him, לא.
lo. Okay. And then he goes on. So that's רבנו חננאל, Rabbeinu
Chananel, and then he says like this. He says,
ויותר נראה, veyoser nireh, three lines before the end of תוספות, Tosafot
towards the beginning of the line, you see where it says? ויותר
נראה, veyoser nireh, but it more appears, דכופין בכל הני, dekofin bechol
hanei, that we actually do physically force. כדפריש ר"י. kedifereish Ri. אלא
דבירושלמי קסבר דשייך כפייה במילי. ela debyerushalmi kasavar deshayach kefia bemilei. It's
true there's a ירושלמי Yerushalmi thinks you can do it just with
words, but from our the בבלי, Bavli, it sounds like you use
force. אבל לדידן דקיימא לן דבדברים לא יוסר עבד, aval ledidan dekaima
lan debidvarim lo yivaser eved, what we hold in a גמרא Gemara
quotes the פסוק pasuk
that you know it says that a slave is not sort
of corrected by just words, meaning the בבלי Bavli takes a more
you know a stronger position on the use of force that sometimes
you really need it. על כרחך איירי בשוטי, al korchacha ayiri beshoti,
we're talking about using sticks, like using real force. כיון דלשון יוציא
משמע כפייה, kivan delashon yotzi mashma kefia, since יוציא sounds like we
force him. היכא דעושה עולה, heicha de'oseh avla, when he's the one
that does the perversion to her, he's the one that's to blame.
ומיהו, umihu, okay, so that's a whole discussion. When it just says
יוציא without כופין kofin להוציא, does יוציא mean we try to get
him to divorce her or does it mean we force him, we
actually use physical force? תוספות Tosafos is inclined to say we use
physical force. Then תוספות Tosafos, says, ומיהו אין לכוף שום אדם לגרש
ולעשות מעשה, umihu ein lichof shum adam legaresh vela'asos ma'aseh, we should
not actually use physical force and to write a גט get. to,
you know, to get the guy to give a גט, get עד
שימצא ראיה ברורה, ad sheyimatze raya berura, unless it's absolutely clear that
he's obligated to give the גט. get. Why? דהא גט מעושה בישראל
שלא כדין פסול, deha get me'useh beyisrael shelo kedin pasul, even though
this is being forced by a Jewish court, but if it was
an improper ruling, the גט get would be invalid. Okay, so even
though you're allowed to use a Jewish court to force only if
it's only if it's legitimate. ואין להתיר אשת איש מספק. ve'ein lehatir
eshes ish misafek. So we have to be very careful. So this
תוספות Tosafos. nicely encapsulates a lot of the dynamic that goes on
right now in the בתי דין batei din in ישראל, Yisrael, right?
You have those that are basically like don't are basically against any
type of pressure all together, let alone not בשוטי, beshoti, not even
words or others. You know, you have those that may be in
principle the court is empowered to do a lot of things in
terms of taking away driver's license, putting the person in prison, etcetera,
etcetera, but they're always very afraid. So maybe in principle you have
כופין even בשוטי, beshoti, you know, even though a lot of that
is not בשוטי, beshoti, it's just revoking privileges, it's not you know
except you know except not actually like physical force, at least some
of those things. Anyway, but then in the end it says oh,
but maybe according to this שיטה, shita, it's not justified, it'll be
a גט מעושה בישראל get me'useh beyisrael and it'll be פסול. pasul.
So you get a lot of this hesitancy that kicks in, you
know even if in principle you're allowed to use force. So this
תוספות Tosafos nicely encapsulates a lot of like current dynamics around these
issues.
Yes. Two questions on that. Well I guess I'll start with this
latest point, that if you say כל המקדש אדעתא דרבנן מקדש, kol
hamekaidesh adata derabanan mekaidesh, and if a court gets involved and he's
מקדש mekaidesh on the premise that the court can get involved when
necessary, so I don't know why it would be פסול. pasul.
But the other one is, all right, I'm not going into that.
That's about when you use הפקעה. hafka'ah. Okay.
The other one is, also רש"י Rashi says אין הנאת תשמיש נאסרה
עליו ein hana'as tashmish ne'esra alav because יש לו בה, yesh lo
bah, and I don't understand that. We had that in ע"א ayin
alef regarding איסור תשמיש המיטה issur tashmish hamita works, you know, you
get like a... So maybe I mean so that תוספות Tosafos read
because otherwise this משנה Mishna would be sort of repetitious so maybe
unless you say תשמיש Tashmish doesn't mean תשמיש tashmish. but I'm not
understanding רש"י Rashi why why he's saying that he can't do it.
I mean we have a משנה Mishna beforehand that says that you
can but then you know that whole ביטל. Bitel. So that's תוספות's
Tosafos question. תוספות Tosafos says take a look תוספות Tosafos. says he
says אם כן מתשמיש עמי חל הנדר Im ken mitashmish amei chal
haneder I mean that he basically that's actually no that's according to
the גמרא Gemara that's talking about ארוסה Arusa but the case before
about בית הלל Beis Hillel בית שמאי. Beis Shammai.
Yeah so רש"י Rashi addresses that כגון
דאמר יאסר הנאת תשמישך עלי אבל הנאת תשמישי עליך לא מיתסרא דהא
משועבד לה. Kegon de-amar ye-aser hana-as tashmishecha alai aval hana-as tashmishi alecha
lo misra de-ha meshubad lah. Okay so when he makes her הנאה
hana-ah forbidden to him he's not directly undercut he's dealing with his
own deriving of benefit. But if he says his הנאה hana-ah of
his having sex with her is forbidden to her he can't he's
not a בעל הבית ba-al habayis and he has an obligation.
Yes. רמב"ם Rambam lashes even for not giving the right amount of
charity. Does he comment on this?
Well רמבם Rambam also has כפייה בגט. kefiyah be-get. I forget whether
רמב"ם's exact by this yeah but certainly everybody holds with the idea
of כפייה בגט. kefiyah be-get. The question is what are the circumstances?
Yeah.
Do you refer to Israeli courts? You mean Rabbinic?
Yeah I meant Rabbinic.
And they have such authority?
Yeah Rabbinic courts have the sole authority over laws of גט. get.
Can they put somebody in prison?
Yeah. Yeah but they never use it or almost never. Okay so
now let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara but yes Michael
correctly reminds us that there's ways a person could make sex forbidden
by forbidding the wife's the pleasure of the wife's sex on him
but anyway here we'd be talking that he's forbidding his pleasure on
her which he's not entitled to do about something that he has
a right to. So רש"י Rashi, says okay well she's got a
right to sex so it doesn't work for the sex. תוספות Tosafos
says no it's just the language doesn't include sex. Now the גמרא's
Gemara. going to say but she's got also the right for מזונות.
Mezonot So how is he able to do it? So let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara גמרא Gemara says וכיון דמשועבד לה
היכי מצי מדר לה Ve-keivan de-meshubad lah heichi matzi madar lah since
he is obligated to her for מזונות Mezonot, how can he make
the נדר neder like it's basically her
מזונות? Mezonot, So how is he entitled to make the נדר? neder?
כל כמיניה דמפקע ליה לשיבודיה Kol keminei de-mafka lei le-shibudei does he
have the power to uproot her שיבוד shibud her right to her
מזונות? Mezonot So the גמרא Gemara says ודתנן ve-hasnan we taught in
the משנה Mishnah, קונם שאיני עושה לפיך konam she-eini osah le-picha
if the woman tries to forbid her מעשה ידיים ma-aseh yadayim right
the counterpart to the מזונות Mezonot, to the husband and she says
הקדש hekdesh קונם konam is a language of
נדר neder a נדר neder anything that I'm producing with my hands
is forbidden to your mouth so she's trying to forbid her product
her production of מעשה ידיים ma-aseh yadayim to him אינו צריך להפר
einu tzarich lehafer he doesn't have to annul. אלמא כיון דמשועבדא ליה
לאו כל כמינה דמפקעה ליה לשיבודיה Alma keivan de-meshubda lei lav kol
keminei de-mafka lei le-shibudei since the things that she is obligated to
him and that he has rights to
she doesn't have the power to undermine his שיבוד. shibud. Now I
should say that the thing that this is parallel to that you
might be thinking about is like מושבע ועומד מהר סיני mushba ve-omed
me-har sinai but that's different. Again remember נדר neder is about the
object שבועה shevuah is about the person. So if I actually have
an obligation to sit in a סוכה sukkah and I say שבועה
shevuah that I won't sit in a סוכה sukkah on סוכות sukkos
so that personal obligation that I am putting upon myself can't contradict
the obligation I have on me from הר סיני. har sinai. I
am מושבע ועומד מהר סיני mushba ve-omed me-har sinai I have a
prior שבועה shevuah from הר סיני har sinai to sit in a
סוכה sukkah I can't obligate myself not to. Here you're referring to
the object. So actually a way you can forbid sitting in a
סוכה sukkah on yourself is if you said הנאת סוכה אסורה עלי
ישיבת סוכה אסורה עלי. hana-as sukkah asurah alai yeshivas sukkah asurah alai.
הנאה hana-ah by the way would be apart from so then you're
indirectly undercutting it by making the object forbidden to you not directly
going against your
obligation of סוכה. sukkah. So here it's not enough to say oh
he can't make it אסור assur he's obligated. Alright he's not saying
he doesn't have to provide he's just making the object forbidden. So
the problem here is not his obligation. Notice the גמרא Gemara doesn't
say he's מושבע ועומד mushba ve-omed or he's חייב. chayav. The problem
here is who owns the object? You got it? When it comes
to a שבועה shevuah the question is you can't go against your
obligation. When it comes to a נדר neder actually that is a
way to undermine your obligation but the question is it only works
when things that are your objects. If you're making forbidden on somebody
else you can't make somebody else's object forbidden to you. So to
make the מעשה ידיים ma-aseh yadayim forbidden to the husband it has
to be hers. If he has rights to it it's not enough
hers to make his מזונות Mezonot. forbidden to her. It has to
be his. If she has rights to it, it's not enough his.
So that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying: הכא נמי כיון דמשועבד
לה, Hacha nami keivan demeshubad la, since he has an obligation to
her, לאו כל כמיניה דמפקע ליה לשעבודא, lav kol kaminei demaphka lei
leshibuda, he doesn't have the power to undermine her lien as it
were, her lien on that on the מזונות, Mezonot her rights to
the מזונות. Mezonot It's not enough his object, it's her object, she
can't, he can't make it forbidden to her. אלא, Ella, so how
does it work? How can he make it forbidden? מתוך שיכול לומר
לה צאי מעשה ידיך במזונותייך, Mitoche sheyachol lomar la tzeii maaseh yadayich
bimezonotayich, because in theory he can say to her, and remember this
is the question of who is in the power to call off
the deal in terms of מזונות Mezonot and מעשה ידיים. Maaseh Yadayim.
So assuming he has the power, since he could say to her
look, you keep your מעשה ידיים, Maaseh Yadayim, I'm not gonna give
you מזונות, Mezonot. assuming he has that power, so he really is
the בעל הבית, Baal Habayit, right? If he at any time could
say I'm keeping the מזונות, Mezonot, you keep your מעשה ידיים, Maaseh
Yadayim, then he really ultimately is the one who is the owner
of those מזונות Mezonot because he can basically call off the deal
at any time. So since he could do that, say keep your
מעשה ידיים, Maaseh Yadayim, I'll keep the
מזונות, Mezonot, נעשה כאומר לה, Naaseh keomer la, it's as if he
said to her צאי מעשה ידיך במזונותייך. Tzeii maaseh yadayich bimezonotayich. You
know, you keep your מעשה ידיים Maaseh Yadayim and I'll keep the
מזונות. Mezonot, Basically what it's saying is no, he is the boss
of the מזונות Mezonot. because he's in the power to say I'm
keeping it and you keep your מעשה ידיים. Maaseh Yadayim. Okay, now
let's take a look. That assumes that he's in that position.
Now the גמרא Gemara says ואי איתא להא דרב הונא אמר רב,
Vei ita leha deRav Huna amar Rav, now if we hold of
the position however רב הונא אמר רב, Rav Huna amar Rav, what
does רב הונא Rav Huna say in the name of רב? Rav?
דאמר רב הונא אמר רב יכולה אשה שתאמר לבעלה, Damar Rav Huna
amar Rav yachola ishah shetomar levaala, a woman can say to her
husband איני ניזונת ואיני עושה, Eini nizonet veeini osah, that she's in
the position of power. She can say I'm not going to be
fed by you and I'm not going to do work for you,
I'll keep my מעשה ידיים. Maaseh Yadayim. So according to that approach
that she's the בעל הבית Baal Habayit of her מעשה ידיים, Maaseh
Yadayim, she could choose to call it off. So if that's true,
קונם שאני עושה לפיך מאי איכא למימר? Konam sheani osah leficha mai
ika lemeimar? Let's go back to that other example, right, we have
these two parallel examples we're looking at. Him forbidding his מזונות Mezonot,
on her, her forbidding her מעשה ידיים Maaseh Yadayim on him. So
we said how could he forbid his מזונות mezonot. on her? Because
he is the boss, he can call it off, he can keep
the מזונות. mezonot But says one minute, there's an opinion that she
is the boss of the מעשה ידיים, Maaseh Yadayim, she can choose
to call it off and keep her מעשה ידיים. Maaseh Yadayim. So
if that's true, why can't she forbid her מעשה ידיים Maaseh Yadayim
on him? Should be the same argument. So
נעשה כמי שאומרת לו, Naaseh kemi sheomeret lo, let it be like
she said to him איני ניזונת ואיני עושה, Eini nizonet veeini osah,
like she said I'm keeping my מעשה ידיים, Maaseh Yadayim, they're forbidden
to you. So if that idea that you can call it off
makes you the boss and makes you the one who owns it,
then why shouldn't it work in that case as well when she's
forbidding the מעשה ידיים? Maaseh Yadayim? So the גמרא Gemara said אלא
Ella you're right. If you don't say it explicitly and the arrangement
still holds, you're not the boss. לא תימא נעשה, Lo teima naaseh,
it wouldn't be it's as if you said that. It's not enough
in potential you could call off the arrangement. As long as the
arrangement still stands, you're not the boss and you can't make it
forbidden with a נדר. Neder. אלא Ella is a case where it
works is באומר לה Beomer la when he explicitly says צאי מעשה
ידיך במזונותייך. Tzeii maaseh yadayich bimezonotayich. He explicitly said we're calling off
the arrangement. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says we have this case
that the woman can't forbid her מעשה ידיים. Maaseh Yadayim. The only
way you can understand that, why don't we say she's the boss,
is that it's not enough to have the potential to call off
the arrangement. As long as the arrangement stands, you're not the boss
and you can't make it forbidden with a נדר. Neder. It only
works if you actually have called off the arrangement and now you
actually do become the boss. So if she calls off the arrangement
and she says I'm keeping my מעשה ידיים, Maaseh Yadayim, then of
course she can say that they're אסור Assur to you for a
נדר. Neder. Similarly, if he called off the arrangement and said I'm
keeping the מזונות, mezonos. you keep your מעשה ידיים, Maaseh Yadayim, then
the מזונות mezonos, become his and therefore he can make it forbidden
to her with a נדר. Neder. Of course, the question is if
that's what he did, then why do you have to get divorced?
What's the problem? Right? He keeps he keeps the מזונות, mezonos she
keeps her מעשה ידיים, Maaseh Yadayim, let him make it אסור Assur
by נדר, Neder, who cares about any of this? Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara, says the earlier answer was really like a better answer,
you know, conceptually. Since in theory he could, he's entitled, you know,
it works. But now if he actually has called off the arrangement,
so אי הכי Ei hachi says the גמרא, Gemara פרנס למה לי?
Parnas lama li? Who needs a third party to provide for her?
He's called off the arrangement. So the גמרא Gemara says בדלא ספקא.
Bidelo sapka. Ah, no. The point problem is you're only entitled to
say I'm keeping my מזונות, mezonos you keep your מעשה ידיים Maaseh
Yadayim if your מעשה ידיים Maaseh Yadayim you earn enough to provide
for yourself, for your מזונות. mezonos But if you don't earn enough
to provide for your מזונות, mezonos then I, the husband, still have
to make up the difference. So if I still have to make
up the difference, we need a third party to make up the
difference. Of course, the problem is if I have to make up
the difference, we're back to square one, the נדר Neder doesn't take
effect on that difference. So the גמרא Gemara says אי בדלא ספקא,
Ei bidelo sapka,
if the מעשה ידיים Maaseh Yadayim don't aren't sufficient, הדרא קושיין לדוכתא,
Hadra kushyan ledouchta, we go back to our original question. The obligation
of the husband, the difference that he has to make up, is
hers. He's not entitled to make it. forbidden? So אמר רב אשי
amar Rav Ashi במספקת לדברים גדולים ואינה מספקת לדברים קטנים. bemisfeket l'devarim
gedolim v'eina misfeket l'devarim ktanim. No,
no, no, her מעשה ידיים ma'asei yadayim covers all the big expenses,
you know, all of the food, all of the ever, whatever, the
domicile, all the big expenses is covered. The little expenses are not
covered. Okay, and therefore that's what the problem is. Of course we're
still going to be back to square one, right? Because make up
your mind, either he's obligated or not obligated. The גמרא Gemara. says
הני דברים קטנים היכי דמי? hanei devarim ktanim heichi dami? What are
these little things that are that that her מעשה ידיים ma'asei yadayim
don't cover? אי דרגילה בהו, ei deregila behu, if she's accustomed to
them, הא רגילה בהו, ha regila behu, she's accustomed and he's obligated,
and if he's obligated we're back to question one, which is the
נדר neder shouldn't take effect. ואי דלא רגילה בהו, v'ei delo regila
behu, if they're things that she's not accustomed to, like you know,
opportunity to go, I don't know, to Disneyland or whatever, or to
buy an iPod, or things like that, those little things, so you
know, whatever, you know, so if that's not the normal her normal
standard of living, so he's not obligated, but and if he's not
obligated, the נדר neder takes effect, but if the נדר neder takes
effect, he doesn't have to have a third party, there's no problem
here, there was no obligation. פרנס למה לי? parnas lama lei? Who
needs a third lama lei, who needs a third party? לא צריכא,
lo tzricha, you need it for the following case: דרגילה בבית נשא,
deregila beveit nasha, she's she was accustomed to it in her father's
house,
וקמגלגלא בהדיה, vekamgalgela bahadeih, and she's willing to go along with him,
like he says in her father's house she would always you know
whatever, I don't know, we have to come up with some small
thing. She would always get a a manicure once a week. Her
father would always treat her to a manicure once a week. She
gets married to this guy and no, that's like and no you
know that's not his standard of living, and therefore they don't cover
that. Okay, so she says fine, I'm living with you, I'm living
with you even though the הלכה halacha is עולה עמו ואינה יורדת
עמו, olah imo ve'eina yoredet imo, that you're entitled to keep me
to that standard that I was living, I'll tolerate it, okay, we're
living together, I'll live according to your standard of living, she's essentially
מוחלת. mochelet. Okay, she's agreed to be מוחל mochel as long as
she's living with him. דאמר ליה, de'amar lei, but now that he
took a vow, that changes everything because technically he's obligated. It's just
that she was willing to be מוחל mochel as long as they
were living together. Now she says to him, עד השתא דלא אדרתן,
ad hashta delo adartan, until now that you didn't take a vow
against me, גלגלינא בהדך, galgelina bahadeich,
I was willing to roll along with you, I was willing to
make do. השתא דאדרתן, hashta de'adartan, now that you took a vow,
לא מצינא דאגלגל בהדך, lo matzina de'egalgel bahadeich, I can't, I won't
roll along with you. So meaning, what is how we conceptualize it?
Basically, he basically is saying I no longer have a חיוב מזונות
chiyuv mezonot to you, you keep your מעשה ידיים, ma'asei yadayim, I
keep my מזונות. mezonos Okay, and therefore the vow of מזונות mezonos,
works, but it's not a problem because he has no חיוב chiyuv
to her. But the vow also now is he's also now taking
a vow on something, but he still would have had before he
took the vow had in theory an obligation to provide for these
דברים קטנים. devarim ktanim. Okay, to provide for the weekly manicure, except
that she was מוחלת mochelet on it. But that was his obligation,
okay? So during, here's the way תוספות Tosafos conceptualizes it. Right now
at this moment she's מוחלת. mochelet. So that cost is my money,
not her money, because she right now is מוחלת. mochelet. As long
as she's מוחלת mochelet it's my money. I can take a vow
on that cost, on on those ten dollars a week that she's
you know generally being מוחלת mochelet for the cost of the manicure.
Everybody with me here? Okay, so she's מוחלת mochelet on it, it's
my money, I can take a vow. As soon as I've taken
a vow, she stops being מוחלת. mochelet. Because oh, you're now you're
not you know here I am, I'm accommodating you, and you're now
there's this whatever thing going between us that you make a vow
to forbid it or whatever. As soon as it's forbidden, then I
want it, you know or whatever, not just then I want it,
but then like clearly I'm not going to accommodate you. So as
soon as he takes the vow, the vow works because at that
moment she was מוחלת, mochelet, but as soon as it worked he
becomes obligated and now he can't satisfy his obligation. פארכאפט! farkhapt! So
he becomes obligated, he can't satisfy it, and now we gotta have
somebody else to provide, and we actually have the problem that if
it lasts too long they gotta get divorced. Now really just for
these little דברים קטנים devarim ktanim that she was willing to be
מוחלת mochelet on? So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. ומאי שנא שלשים יום?
u'mai shna shloshim yom? So what does thirty days matter? עד שלשים
יום לא שמעי בה אינשי. ad shloshim yom lo sham'ei bah inshi.
Until thirty days people don't know about it, the gossips aren't in
high form yet, ולא זילא בה מילתא, velo zila bah milta, it's
not embarrassing. טפי שמעי בה אינשי, tfei sham'ei bah inshi, more than
thirty days people, hey I heard that the husband has taken a
vow to prevent his wife from getting benefit, whatever that benefit might
be, okay, that's making an announcement that there's trouble in the marriage
and that the husband is mistreating the wife and the wife is
sort of tolerating it or whatever. So in those cases זילא בה
מילתא, zila bah milta, that is degrading to her and therefore we
will not tolerate it more than that. Only up to that point
before it becomes a public matter can we see if we can
sort of allow it or see if we can work something out.
What if it becomes a public matter earlier? What? You need anything?
No, you know, the גמרא Gemara sort of doesn't look at it.
אי בעית אימא, ei ba'it eima, so that's one answer. One answer
was these little like דברים קטנים, devarim ktanim, okay, that she was
being מוחלת, mochelet, but as soon as he took the vow it
became a problem. אי בעית אימא, ei ba'it eima, and if you
want you could say... שהדירה כשהיא ארוסה. shehidira keshi'erusa. Here's how it
works. He took the vow when she was just an ארוסה. erusa.
So she was just an ארוסה, erusa, he wasn't yet obligated, so
the vow kicked in. Okay? Of course, if the vow kicked in
and she wasn't obligated, why does it become a, why do they
have to get divorced? He was entitled to take this vow at
this time. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara, says
ארוסה מי של מזוני? arusa mi shelei mezoni? She's not entitled to
מזונות. mezonot So what's the whole problem? You know?
שיגיע זמן ולא נישאו. sheyagia zman velo niso.
Right. Very good, Michael. שיגיע זמן ולא נישאו. sheyagia zman velo niso.
No, because the time has come to get married and they haven't
gotten married, so now he does have an obligation.
תנן, Tenan, the משנה, mishna הגיע זמן ולא נישאו אוכלת משלו ואוכלת
בתרומה. higia zman velo niso ocheles mishelo ve'ocheles bitruma. That once it's,
you know, the time is, it's a year from the time that
they asked to get married, if one of them asked to get
married, they should be and if it's not, he has to be
providing for her. Okay. So therefore what? So why, and this is
the רש"י Rashi that I was thinking about before. Why is this
different before the time that she was an ארוסה erusa and now
it's שלושים יום? shloshim yom? Once it becomes the time period where,
once it becomes, like everybody says if it's the time period that
he's obligated to provide for her even if she's not a נשואה,
nesua, then we're back to square one and how does the נדר
neder take effect? Okay, he's obligated, he's obligated. So here was the
רש"י Rashi I was thinking about before. I was confused before. רש"י
Rashi says, look at רש"י, Rashi
רש"י Rashi?
says ולא נישאו, velo niso, the four lines from the top, last
of the wide lines, דמדאורייתא לא משתעבד לה, הלכך חל הנדר דאיסור
דאורייתא הוא, ומדרבנן חייב למזונה, הלכך יעמיד פרנס. demide'oraisa lo mishtabed la,
hilkach chal haneder de'issur de'oraisa hu, umiderabbanan chayav limzona, hilkach yamid parnas.
So רש"י Rashi says it takes effect because at this period of
before they actually have נישואין, nisuin, it's only a רבנן Rabbanan obligation
to provide. So the נדר neder kicks in and therefore, but he
still has this רבנן Rabbanan obligation. So in that case, the נדר
neder kicked in because it was only רבנן, Rabbanan, but he's not
satisfying his obligation. So therefore, has to provide to a third party
or maybe have to get divorced. So רש"י Rashi: says when the
obligation is only רבנן, Rabbanan, the נדר neder actually will kick in.
Of course, what רש"י Rashi suggests here is is that once they
actually do get married, what does it sound like from רש"י? Rashi
That the obligation is דאורייתא. de'oraisa. Okay? So and anybody who's learned,
you know, חומש Chumash with רש"י Rashi will tell you immediately. What
does it mean when it says שארה כסותה ועונתה לא יגרע? she'era
kesusa ve'onasa lo yigra? רש"י: Rashi, שארה she'era is מזונות, mezonot, כסותה
kesusa is clothes, ועונתה ve'onasa is תשמיש. tashmish. Of course, רמב"ן Ramban
and תוספות Tosafos all get up and yell. They say, "Very nice,
but we פסק pasken actually that מזונות mezonot. and the כסות kesus
is דרבנן, derabbanan. not דאורייתא." de'oraisa. But רש"י Rashi, seems to consistently
hold that מזונות mezonot, is דאורייתא. deoraita. This רש"י Rashi, as well.
So רש"י Rashi is holding to take the vow once they're already
נשואין, nisuin, it won't take effect, that's דאורייתא. de'oraisa, To take it
when it's an ארוסה erusa and when you have a רבנן Rabbanan
obligation because it's been a year and so on, that's רבנן, Rabbanan,
it will take effect. תוספות, Tosafot take a look at תוספות. Tosafot,
תוספות Tosfos says שהגיע זמן ולא נישאו. shehigia zman velo niso. תוספות
says,
פירש בקונטרס דמדאורייתא לא משתעבד לה, הלכך הנדר חל. וקשה, אם כן
מן הנישואין נמי לא יחול הנדר, מהאי טעמא דקיימא לן דמזונות נשואה
דרבנן.
peirush bakuntres demide'oraisa lo mishtabed la, hilkach haneder chal. vekasheh,
im kein min hanisuin nami lo yachol haneder, mehai ta'ama dekaima lan
de mezonos nesua derabbanan. Okay, תוספות says, I gotta tell you רש"י,
I gotta tell you, מזונות mezonot. is דרבנן even after נישואין. nisuin.
Okay, so תוספות says, I'm skipping a few lines, lines that say
ונראה venireh in the middle of
תוספות. ונראה לפרש שהגיע זמן ולא נישאו כלומר הך דתני יעמיד פרנס
עד שיגיע זמן ולא נישאו קאי כשנדר עדיין לא הגיע זמן, הלכך
חל הנדר. venireh lefareish shehigia zman velo niso kolomar hach detani yamid
parnas ad sheyagia zman velo niso kai keshenadar adayin lo higia zman,
hilkach chal haneder. Okay, so תוספות says, No, רש"י, you got it
wrong. It's all דרבנן. But even a חיוב דרבנן chiyuv derabbanan
could resist the נדר. neder. Bottom line is, remember, this is not
שבועה. shvua. A שבועה shvua idea is, I have a חיוב, chiyuv,
I have a חיוב chiyuv מהר סיני, mehar Sinai, I can't take
a שבועה shvua against it. If my חיוב chiyuv is only רבנן,
Rabbanan, I can take a שבועה shvua against my חיוב, chiyuv, but
I can't take a שבועה shvua against my biblical חיוב. chiyuv. But
here, it's not about obligation. Here, what did I tell you it
was about by the נדר? neder? What prevents the נדר neder from
taking effect? Not the degree of obligation but the חפץ cheftza and
who owns the object? It's a question of ownership. It's not a
question of obligation. So תוספות says even if your obligation is only
רבנן, Rabbanan, it's not a question of does this outweigh my obligation?
Bottom line is, who owns the מזונות mezonos now? Even if it
was only the רבנים Rabbanim who made me obligated, right now my
wife owns the מזונות mezonos and not me. Okay? So two very
important issues here. The idea of שבועה shvua is I'm obligated, I
can't take a שבועה shvua against my biblical obligation. If it's only
רבנן, Rabbanan, then my שבועה shvua is more weighty than my רבנן
Rabbanan obligation. By נדר, neder, it's about the object. Question is not
the weight of obligation, the question is who owns it. So therefore,
תוספות says even if your obligation is only רבנן, Rabbanan, since your
wife owns the מזונות, mezonos. therefore your נדר neder cannot counteract it.
Okay? So רש"י, however, brings in... and again repeating his position that
מזונות mezonos by a נשואה nesua is דאורייתא. So back to the
גמרא, Gemara what does תוספות think the answer is? The answer is
the following: how did the נדר neder take effect? The נדר neder
took effect when you were a, when she was an ארוסה. arusa.
Then there was no obligation. Way early when she was an ארוסה.
arusa. Now the twelve months have kicked in, okay, and now there
is an obligation, but he can't satisfy his obligation because the נדר
neder already took effect. You got it? The נדר neder took effect
at a time prior to the obligation, when she was an ארוסה
arusa and the time had not run up. Now that it's been
twelve months, so the נדר's neder already there, now it's the twelve
months, now he can't satisfy his obligation.
Wait, you said thirty, mean thirty days past the time where he
needed to report or... Yeah, so he really is like his נדר's
neder like thirty-three days or whatever it is, right? Like he did
it three days before when he still could do it, right? Because
you're not allowed to take a נדר neder one...
No, he took his, no no no, he took his נדר neder
a year before this became an issue. He took his נדר neder
when she was just an ארוסה. arusa. Okay, she was ten years
old. Then she was fifteen, five years later and they said let's
get married. And then a year from that she's sixteen, they're still
not married, and then he's obligated to support her. His נדר's neder
been in place for six years.
Wait no no no no, I mean when we say like thirty
days, I mean thirty days before obligation. So what I'm saying is
he had to have done at least a נדר neder more than
thirty days before.
Much more, he did it a year before.
Wait, at least at least...
It would have to be a year because of this case.
Okay. What? No, he took the נדר, neder, he took the נדר,
neder, okay. ומאי שנא שלשים יום, Umai shna shloshim yom,
so why thirty days? Okay, because she's not even married yet. Okay,
so presumably the גמרא Gemara assumes that she's not going to be
embarrassed that there is a נדר neder if they're not yet married.
Like then it doesn't become a whole public issue or even if
it is, maybe it's not as big of a deal, they're not
yet married, okay, because people always fight before the wedding. ומאי שנא
שלשים יום, Umai shna shloshim yom, עד שלשים יום עבדי אינשי דיכולה
ad shloshim yom avdi insha d'yachalsa because up to thirty days we
can assume that the third party is going to take care of
his responsibilities. טפי לא עבדי אינשי דיכולה, Tfei lo avdi insha d'yachalsa,
more than that we can't assume. Okay, so that's one answer and
it's a very different idea of the thirty days, not that it's
intolerable, because if they're not yet married it's not so intolerable. It's
only intolerable to have this situation if they're married. Okay, so this
makes it though they're not married, but he has an obligation of
מזונות, mezonos. but following תוספות, the נדר neder took effect before the
obligation of מזונות.
mezonos What you just said before.
ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'it eima, it's a different answer, ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'it eima,
and the third possibility is בדידה כשהיא ארוסה וניסת. b'didah k'shehi arusa
v'niseis. Okay, so now an even easier case. Why did we say
he took the vow when she was an ארוסה arusa and then
became the year and time for start supporting her because it's the
time to get married? Once you're giving the scenario that he took
the vow when it could be binding, the easiest scenario is he
took the vow when she was an ארוסה arusa and now they
got married. Right? Everybody see how structurally this is the exact same
as we said before? Except rather than saying a vow when she
was an ארוסה arusa and then it's time to get married and
he has to start supporting her, why not say a vow when
she was an ארוסה arusa now they actually got married and it's
time to start supporting her? Yes.
Are we using the words vow and נדר neder interchangeably?
Yes, I'm using vow for נדר. neder.
But even though we made the distinction earlier,
שבועה shvua is an oath, not a vow. Okay, I mean that's
at least the standard distinction. Okay, so okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says one minute, here's why we didn't give that easier answer before.
ניסת, Niseis, if she got married and the vow was already in
place, הסברה וקבלה. hasabra v'kibla. She waited, she considered it, and she
accepted it. She knew what she was getting herself into. Here's the
difference: a woman doesn't have to go to the חופה chuppah if
she's not ready, right? If she doesn't want to. So when we
said it was the time to get married, she didn't agree to
anything. He took a vow, it's the time to get married, they're
not getting married, he's obligated מזונות, mezonos? she's not happy with the
situation. So that creates this problem, he has an obligation to feed
her and he's not doing it. But if she actually went to
the חופה chuppah with this vow in place, she's implicitly saying I'm
okay with the situation. So then what's the problem? הסברה וקבלה. Hasabra
v'kibla. No, דאמרה כסבורה אני שיכולה אני לקבל ועכשיו אין אני יכולה
לקבל. de'amra k'sveura ani she'yechola l'kabel, achshav eini yechola l'kabel.
I thought I could manage it, I thought I could manage living
together. Look, it's not like I'm earning my own money, right? I
mean we have that whole issue that her צאן tzon מעשה ידיה
ma'aseh yadeha and he has to basically, oh actually no, we don't
have to do the מעשה... ma'aseh... well presumably she'd be entitled to
keep her מעשה ידיה ma'aseh yadeha once she can't get his מזונות.
mezonos, So I thought I could manage but I can't. There's, you
know, there's too much distance between us with this vow present and
so on, I thought I could manage. So the גמרא Gemara, says
one minute, אימא דאמרינן הכי גבי מומין. eima d'amrinan hachi gabi mumim.
When do we say that the woman said I thought I could
manage, that's when it came to like the guy has certain blemishes,
he's smelly, other types of things where she said I thought I
could live with it, now I'm finding out that to be in
such intimacy and close quarters with this guy I can't live with
it. But לענין מזוני, l'inyan mezonei, but when it's a question about
just providing food... מי אמרינן הכי? mi amrinan hachi? She knew that
she would have to provide her own food. What new occurred that
she didn't realize? Now, so אלא, ela, says the גמרא, Gemara מחורתא
כדשנינן מעיקרא, machvarta kedeshnin meikara, it's better that we said before that
if she actually agrees to get married with that vow in place,
she's implicitly saying she's okay and she does not have a legitimate
claim saying I didn't anticipate how difficult it would be. What was
there for you not to anticipate? You knew you'd have to be
providing for your own food bill. Of course, as I was trying
to say before, there is a reasonable הוה אמינא, hava amina, like
the גמרא Gemara said before. The נדר neder doesn't just mean that
she's paying the bills, it creates this like chill, this like wall
in the marriage and she said I didn't realize how much that
would know create this distance between us, but the גמרא Gemara does
not consider that. So the basic question is how do you have
it that the vow takes effect and he's not satisfying his obligation?
If he's obligated, it shouldn't have taken effect. And basically the גמרא
Gemara settles on two answers. One is for these little things which
technically he's obligated but she had been מוחל mocheil and now the
vow becomes this big, you know, distancing thing between them, and now
it becomes that he that she really does demand that he start
providing for those things, or that he put the vow when she
was an ארוסה arusa and now he does have an obligation. Not
that she got married, 'cause then she would be saying she's okay
with this, but the time has come to start providing and therefore
and he's not providing. Yes.
And at the beginning of the משנה mishna. we were saying that
even though we said he took the vow, it was actually her
vow that he didn't negate.
No, that's what we said in the second part of the משנה.
mishna The first part of the משנה mishna, was his vow. The
second part 'cause the first part was actually saying that his that
his sex, you know, that he was forbidding the benefit of his
benefit on her. He was preventing the benefit of him providing the
מזונות mezonos to her.
The first part was the simple case. It was his vow. It
was only the second part that we had to say that it
was a case of her vow. I want to say one other
thing... it is his vow, yes. Where we're... yeah. All we've been
talking about today, ignore the end of the משנה, mishna all we've
been talking about today is the case of him vowing to forbid
the... the תשמיש. Okay, so we've seen some interesting things. I spoke
about the difference between שבועה shvua and נדר neder and about degree
of obligation and תוספות'ס point that even if it's only רבנן rabbinic
obligation, here it's not about obligation, it's about ownership, and therefore the
issue about רש"י about like I said about whether מזונות is דאורייתא,
but also what I wanted to go back and of course to
is one thing I skipped over which is very important. Who's in
charge? Who is in the position to say we're calling it off?
Okay. The גמרא Gemara switched between saying he can say, not calling
off the marriage, the מעשה ידיים ma'aseh yadayim and מזונות. He can
say I am keeping the מזונות and you keep your מעשה ידיים.
ma'aseh yadayim. Then it quoted the other opinion that said she could
say I'm keeping my מעשה ידיים ma'aseh yadayim you keep your מזונות.
That's very important, right? Who's the fundamental party that's protected? So we've
got a problem though, say the פוסקים, poskim, which is we פסקן
pasken she's in charge. We פסקן pasken not now, but in later
in the גמרא Gemara it will say we פסקן pasken יכולה אשה
שתאמר לבעלה איני ניזונת ואיני עושה. yechola isha shetomar leba'ala eini nizonos
ve'eini osa. The woman is able to say you keep your מזונות
I keep my מעשה ידיים. ma'aseh yadayim. So if she's in charge,
they go back and say how do we make sense, right, of
the fact that the גמרא Gemara explained that the case of the
משנה Mishna: was when he said you keep your מעשה ידיים ma'aseh
yadayim I'll keep my מזונות? Right? You're not in charge, she's in
charge, right? And how can you say that? Sounds like he's in
charge. So of course there's a third possibility. What's the third possibility?
They're both in charge! Right! Either can call it off! So that
that as long as her מעשה ידיים ma'aseh yadayim are sufficient to
cover the expense, he's entitled to say keep your מעשה ידיים ma'aseh
yadayim I'll keep my מזונות, but she's also entitled to say, and
that's very important because if she's earning a hundred thousand dollars a
year, she can say you keep your מזונות I'll keep my מעשה
ידיים. ma'aseh yadayim. So okay, but and he's only allowed to call
it off if she can provide for herself.
If
she loses her job or something? Does it change in the middle?
Yeah, it might, yeah, because it's not a one-time thing. So if
if things switch and she's no longer able to provide then his
obligation would kick back in. Okay, but that's what we wind up
actually basically saying is that sort of both of them have the
ability but his ability is much more limited than hers, okay. So
that makes
interesting questions,
like what if he gets it in two weeks from now but
this week she doesn't have it, you know?
I know. עד שלושים יום יתפרנס. ad shloshim yom yitparnes. Okay. So
up until thirty days we can tolerate the situation and he can
have a third party. You see that? I come back and all
of a sudden we start falling behind here. So the גמרא Gemara
says ופרנס לאו שליחותיה קעביד? ufarnas lav shlichusei ka'avid? I don't get
it. Isn't this third party just doing the husband's, you know, agency?
So the husband... he's still getting הנאה hana'ah from the husband through
a third party, but he's telling the third party to do it.
So אמר רב הונא באומר כל הזן אינו מפסיד. amar Rav Huna
be'omer kol hazan eino mafsid. No, because what he does is he
does it in a in indirect way. He says anybody who would
who chooses to provide for my wife will won't lose out as
a result. Okay. So when the person actually does it, he's not
actually following the husband's direction, he's doing it totally on his own,
and afterwards the husband decides to give him some money that'll be
very nice. וכי אמר הכי לאו שלחותיה קעביד? Vechi amar hachi lav
shelichutei ka-avid?
Are you telling me that's not considered שליחות? shlichut? דתנן, Detnan, we
taught in the משנה: מי שהיה מושלך בבור, Mi shehayah mushlach babor,
somebody who's down a pit, ואמר, ve-amar, כל השומע קולי יכתוב גט
לאשתו,
kol hashoma koli yichtov
get leishto, whoever hears
my voice should write a גט for my wife, הרי אלו יכתבו
ויתנו, harei elu yichtevu veyitnu, they can write a גט. So when
you say whoever, you still are making a שליח shaliach when a
person chooses to do it. So here too even though you said
whoever, whoever does it, you're still your שליח. shaliach. So the גמרא
Gemara says: No, הכי השתא? hachi hashta? What type of comparison is
that? התם קאמר יכתוב. Hatam ka-amar yichtov. Yes, in both cases you
said whoever. But what was the verb? We're not just talking about
the person who's doing it, right? The verb. In there he said
whoever hears me should write. So should write means you are telling
the person to write, you are commanding whoever opts. Yes, you can
opt to be the one to do it, but if you opt,
I am commanding you, I am directing you to do it. יכתוב,
Yichtov, should write. הכא מי קאמר יזון? Hacha mi ka-amar yazun? Here
you don't say whoever hears me should feed my wife. כל הזן
קאמר, Kol hazan ka-amar, whoever feeds my wife won't lose out as
a result, but I never told you to feed my wife. Okay,
so in one case the who is not filled in, but the
person might not be identified, but you are telling the person to
do it. Here you're not telling the person. Whoever hears will not
lose out as a result. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: והא
בדליקה התירו. Ve-ha bidleika hatiru. But let me give you a case
that's more similar. אמר רבי אמי בדליקה התירו, Amar Rabbi Ami bidleika
hatiru, if a fire broke out they permitted you to say now
the פוסקים poskim actually say that nowadays if a fire broke out
it's סכנת נפשות sakanat nefashot and you do what you need to
do. שבת, Shabbat, this is on שבת, Shabbat, yes, it's סכנת נפשות
sakanat nefashot you need what you need to do. But in case
where it wasn't סכנת נפשות sakanat nefashot and it was just a
concern of property, so in case of fire they allowed לומר כל
המכבה אינו מפסיד, lomar kol hamichabeh eino mafsid,
whoever extinguishes, meaning non-Jew, chooses to extinguish the fire won't lose out
as a result, so the non-Jew comes and they extinguish the fire,
it's not a problem of אמירה לגוי, amira l'goi, I never told
you to do it, and then you can reward them after שבת.
Shabbat. So the גמרא Gemara says: Okay, that seems just like our
case. But the גמרא Gemara says: Yes, but בדליקה, bidleika, he says
by a fire they allowed you to say this. למימרא דמאי? Lememra
de-mai? What's he coming to exclude? לאו למימרא דכי האי גוונא? Lav
lememra de-chi hai gavna? Isn't it coming to exclude a similar case,
about a case meaning by a fire you can do it but
not this case about like taking a נדר neder with your wife,
then it's too much like a case of שליחות? shlichut? So the
גמרא Gemara says: No, לא למימרא שאר איסורים דשבת, lo lememra shear
issurim de-shabbat,
it means by other cases of שבת Shabbat we won't allow you.
Whoever wants to push the elevator button for me won't lose out
as a result, whoever wants to you know whatever, whoever wants to
drive me somewhere won't lose out as a result. No, by other
שבת Shabbat cases we don't allow this type of אמירה לגוי. amira
l'goi. But in the case by the vow we do because technically
speaking it's not a שליחות. shlichut. By the fire we do and
by the vow we do because it's technically not שליחות. shlichut. Okay,
so that's how we get around the idea of the third party.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: מתיב רבא, Metiv Rava, Rava
asked, המודר הנאה מחבירו ואין לו מה יאכל, hamudar hana-ah mechaveiro ve-ein
lo mah yochal, if somebody has a vow, it's forbidden for, you
know to derive benefit, he says I will never take, I take
a vow, I'm so angry at Michael, you know, כל הנאת מייקל
אסור עלי, kol hana-at Michael assur alai, okay, ואין לו מה יאכל,
ve-ein lo mah yochal, but here I am, I'm starving. And Michael,
you know, he's very warm, generous-hearted, he doesn't care that I took
the vow, he's concerned that I have nothing to eat. So what's
Michael going to do? ילך אצל חנווני הרגיל אצלו, Yelech etzel chanvani
haragil etzlo, he goes to a, you know, a shop owner,
like the, you know, the מכולת makolet guy, who he's accustomed to
go to, ויאמר לו, veyomar lo, and Michael says to the מכולת
makolet guy, איש פלוני מודר הנאה ממני,
ish ploni mudar
hana-ah mimeni, so-and-so, you know, he took this vow against me and
he's not allowed to get any benefits from me, ואיני
יודע מה אעשה לו, ve-eini yodeia mah e'eseh lo, but נבך nebach
he's starving, I don't know what I can do for him. הוא
נוטל ונותן לו, Hu notel venoten lo, so the מכולת makolet guy
isn't stupid, he goes ahead and gives me some egg and milk
and whatever other stuff, bread, ובא ונוטל מזה, uba venotel mizeh, and
then he goes to Michael and says, you know what I did?
I did it, and then hey Michael pay me up. Okay, presumably
it sounds like he can demand the money from Michael. Anyway, so
that's the way we did it, we did it by saying like
I don't know what I'm going to do for him. So there
the way it's different is you never said I wish somebody would
provide some egg and milk for him, it's just נבך, nebach, it's
so dark in this room, I don't know what I'm going to
do without the lights on. And then... okay, so then the גמרא
Gemara says: So there you can't specifically specify the action. הכא הוא
דשרי, Hacha hu desharei,
there it's allowed because you don't say somebody needs to feed him,
אבל כל הזן אינו מפסיד, aval kol hazan eino mafsid, whoever feeds
won't lose out, לא, lo, that presumably you're not allowed to do.
The גמרא says: No, לא מיבעיא קאמר, lo mibaya ka-amar, no, it
goes without saying. לא מיבעיא כל הזן אינו מפסיד דלעלמא קאמר, Lo
mibaya kol hazan eino mafsid de-la-alma ka-amar, if you say whoever feeds
won't lose, that's certainly okay, because then you're just, you're generic, you're
saying it to the world, you're not even talking to anybody in
particular. That's much less of a שליחות. shlichut. But האי hai when
you go specifically to a specific person, כיון דרגיל אצלו, keivan de-ragil
etzlo, you're this מכולת makolet guy, you're his regular customer, דקאזיל
וקאמר dekazil veka'amar and you're going and saying this specifically to him.
So in this case it feels much more like a שליחות. shlichus.
כמאן דאמר ליה keman de'amar leh זיל הב ליה את, zil hav
leh at, it's like telling him you go feed him, קמשמע לן
kamashma lan that's okay. So the חידוש chiddush is that's not a
better case, that's a case that actually would have been more problematic.
But תוספות points out if you combine both the problems of both
cases it would not be allowed. If you go to the מכולת
makolet guy and say כל הזן, kol hazan, if כל הזן אינו
מפסיד kol hazan eino mafsid
and you say it specifically to the מכולת makolet guy, that's a
problem because you're combining the specific guy with the specific action. Okay,
but in one case you don't have a specific guy and in
the other case you don't have a specific action. Okay, we will
continue with this tomorrow. All right, I succeeded in getting us behind.
I'm like the guy, I'm like.